

RESEARCHER/ENGINEER IN MACHINE LEARNING FOR ROBOTICS

mingo.esteban@gmail.com | # domingoesteban.com | @ domingoesteban | @ domingoesteban

Summary_

PhD in Advanced and Humanoid Robotics; with an M.Sc. in Robotics and Automation, a B.Sc. in Industrial Engineering and a B.Sc. in Economics and Business. The goal of my research is to endow robots with the ability to autonomously acquire motor skills through a better use of the data obtained from its interaction with the world. My research is mainly supported by the design and application of (deep) reinforcement learning, optimal control and supervised/unsupervised learning techniques.

I am currently working in the Locomotion and Manipulation Group at ANYbotics AG, developing machine learning-based motion control systems for legged robots navigating challenging terrains.

Research Interests

Robot Reinforcement Learning

Model-free and model-based algorithms that scale to robotics problems (high-dimensional, continuous states and actions, hierarchical and multi-task problems)

Optimal Control Control with learned models, control with inaccurate models, Stochastic Optimal Control, MPC

Humanoids and Legged Robots Whole-body motions with various tasks, multi-contact motion, locomotion, loco-manipulation

Imitation Learning Inverse reinforcement learning, shared human-robot representations, behavioral cloning

Education

Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia (IIT) - Università degli Studi di Genova

PHD IN BIOENGINEERING AND ROBOTICS - CURRICULUM: ADVANCED AND HUMANOID ROBOTICS Nov. 2015 - July 2019

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

M.Sc. in Robotics and Automation Sept. 2012 - July 2014

Universidad Nacional de San Agustín de Arequipa

B.Sc. in Industrial Engineering Apr. 2004 - Apr. 2009

Universidad Católica San Pablo

B.Sc. IN ECONOMICS AND BUSINESS

Mar. 2006 - Dec. 2010

Experience

ANYbotics AG Zurich, Switzerland

ROBOTICS SOFTWARE ENGINEER Oct. 2021 - PRESENT

• Development of Machine Learning-based Motion Control Software for Legged Robots.

Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia (IIT) - Dynamic Legged Systems (DLS) lab

Genoa, Italy
Aug. 2019 - Sept. 2021

Genoa, Italy

Madrid, Spain

Arequipa, Peru

Arequipa, Peru

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- Learning and deploying neural networks for predicting foothold and base adjustments in legged robots based on visual feedback.
- Learning locomotion behaviors with model-free Deep Reinforcement Learning techniques in simulation (pybullet, RAISIM simulators, and NVIDIA Isaac Gym).
- Give support to other members of the group in Machine Learning related topics.
- · Writing research project proposals for EU and national funding.

Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia (IIT) – Department of Advanced Robotics (ADVR)

Genoa, Italy

PHD CANDIDATE

Nov. 2015 - July 2019

- · Member of the Learning and Interaction group.
- Research focused on robot learning in humanoid robots:
 - (Deep) reinforcement learning for continuous control tasks: Soft Actor Critic (SAC), Guided Policy Search (GPS), Deep Deterministic Policy Gradients (DDPG), Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), Normalized Advantage Functions (NAF), REPS, PILCO, PI2.
 - Hierarchical and multi-task reinforcement learning in robotics.
 - Exploiting failed executions to improve efficiency and safe-exploration in Reinforcement Learning of robotics tasks.
 - Transfer learning of skills between humanoid robots.
 - Behavioral cloning of whole-body movements

ROBOTICS ENGINEER June 2013 - Oct. 2015

Design, programming and implementation of locomotion, perception, localization, SLAM and motion planning algorithms for the autonomous
robots of the company: unmanned multi-rotors vehicles (UAS), unmanned ground vehicles (UGV) and autonomous underwater vehicles (AUV),
in ROS.

- Simulation of autonomous mobile robots.
- Programming of navigation algorithms for autopilot systems in real-time embedded systems.
- · Programming and implementation of Hardware-in-the-loop (HIL) simulation systems for the navigation of autonomous robots.
- Development and wrapping of sensor drivers in real-time embedded systems.

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

Madrid, Spain

RESEARCH COLLABORATOR - ROBOTICSLAB - HUMANOIDS GROUP

Mar. 2013 - July 2015

- Design, programming and implementation of whole-body trajectory generation algorithms for TEO, the full-size humanoid robot of the Humanoids group.
- Simulation of a humanoid robot in Gazebo simulator.
- Design and development of ROS nodes in C++ and Python.

Publications

2022	Fahmi, S.; Barasuol, V.; Esteban, D. ; Villarreal, O.; Semini, C. "ViTAL: Vision-Based Terrain-Aware Locomotion for Legged Robots",
	IEEE Transactions on Robotics 39 (2)

- **Esteban, D.**; Villarreal, O.; Fahmi, S.; Semini, C.; Barasuol, V. "On the Influence of Body Velocity in Foothold Adaptation for Dynamic Legged Locomotion via CNNs", International Conference on Climbing and Walking Robots (CLAWAR)
- **2019** Esteban, D.; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "Hierarchical reinforcement learning for concurrent discovery of compound and composable policies", IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)
- **2018** Esteban, D.; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "Learning Deep Robot Controllers by Exploiting Successful and Failed Executions", IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)
- Delhaisse, B.*; Esteban, D.*; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "Transfer Learning of Shared Latent Spaces between Robots with Similar Kinematic Structure", IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN) (* Equal contribution)
- Martínez, S.; **Esteban, D.**; Jardón-Huete, A.; Balaguer, C. *"Anticipative Humanoid Postural Control System for Locomotive Tasks"*, IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)

Skills

Machine Learning SW PyTorch, TensorFlow, scikit-learn, OpenAl-Gym, NVIDIA Isaac Gym, GPy

Robotics SW ROS, Gazebo, NVIDIA Isaac Sim, PyBullet, MuJoCo, OpenCV, YARP, RobotStudio **Programming** Python, C++, C, Shell scripting, MATLAB®/Octave, HTML/CSS, Git, Docker

Languages English, Spanish, Italian

Professional Activities

REVIEWER FOR INTERNATIONAL JOURNALS AND CONFERENCES

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

2020, 2021, 2023

SN Applied Sciences

2021, 2022, 2024

International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)

2018, 2019, 2020, 2021

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)

2017, 2018

IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)

2017, 2018

Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)

2018

2021